hello everyone welcome back to my
channel this is part three of twitter
sentiment analysis project series
in this video i have provided the link
in the description to download the
entire code of the project and i will be
explaining how to install and run the
project also i'll explain the working of
the code as much as possible if you have
any doubts do mention it in the comment
section i'll try to explain them in the
subsequent videos
and finally don't forget to like and
subscribe to my channel i'll be posting
more such videos on simple project and
code explanation so do subscribe and
support me
now i'll explain how to run the project
so the first step is to download the
file from the link that i have provided
in the description it contains the
entire code of the project it's a zip
file so you will have to unzip it first
next make sure you have python 3.6 or
greater version installed on your laptop
along with this you also need to add
python path in your system environment
variables
there are certain python libraries that
needs to be installed for the
application to run
so these are the three libraries that we
will be needing for our project and the
procedure to install these libraries is
by opening your command prompt
and typing this syntax and press enter
so the syntax is pip space install space
the library name for example if you want
to install the vp library you have to
enter pip install tp and press enter
similarly if you want to install flash
then enter pip install flask and press
enter
so follow the same procedure to install
all the three libraries and make sure
you have installed all these three
libraries on your system
next make sure you have all the four
keys copied from your twitter developer
account
please watch part 2 of the series if you
haven't created your twitter developer
account yet we'll be needing that for
our project
so these are the four keys that we will
be needing for our project
so make sure you have all these four
keys available with you
next open the project on any ide of your
choice i'll be using vs code
finally you have to run the app.py file
here i am in my vs code editor and i
have opened app.by file
now i will run this
once the app starts running you will get
this message
you can either copy paste this entire
link into your browser or you can just
do control and click to open this
application
now i have copied this link
now i'll paste the link on my browser
the project is now open and working
one more important thing to note is that
the keys that you generate by clicking
on consumer keys has to be copied to
these two variables in the app.py code
consumer key and consumer secret
similarly the case that you generate by
clicking on access token and secret has
to be copied to these two variables in
the app.py code access token and access
token secret
before running the code please make sure
you have pasted the correct keys
corresponding to each of these variables
all you have to do is replace this x
with the actual code that you have
received from twitter developer account
within single quotations
only after that run the application
now i'll explain the directory structure
of the project
within the project folder you'll find
two other folders and one python script
file that is app.py
app.py contains the python code to
run the application
next we have two different folders named
static and templates
templates folder contains all the html
files
index.html will be the home page of our
application or the main page
result.html is the page used to display
the result of phrase level sentiment
analysis and result1.html
is the page used to display the result
of sentence level sentiment analysis
to understand what phrase level and
sentence level sentiment analysis is
please watch part one of the series
next static folder contains all the
static contents that we will be
requiring for our project like the
styling files and the image that will be
using for our application
here within the css folder you will find
two other files
i have used index style dot css file
just to style the
index.html page and resultstyle.css
i have used that to style both result
and result1.html
finally make sure you don't rename or
move any of these files
it will be easier that way
now let us try to understand app.py code
i have actually used the same code
provided in geeksforgeeks website
i have made few changes to this code to
fit for my application
so if you want to get a better
understanding or more information on
this topic you can visit the site and
have a look at it
i have provided the link in description
coming back to our code there are many
different methods that i have used in
the project
i'll explain each of the methods working
let us start by understanding what main
method does so the execution begins from
main method
i have taken four different variables to
store the values of the case that we
obtained from twitter developer account
all you need to do is copy the keys from
twitter developer account and paste it
here within the single quotation
next in these three lines we are trying
to authenticate ourselves to the twitter
api these same keys are used for
authentication process as well after
successful authentication twitter api
object will get created and the object
will be stored in this variable api so
throughout the code i'll be using the
same variable
to refer to the twitter api
if the authentication fails then this
error message will be displayed
next we have app.debug is equal to true
here app refers to the flask application
that i have declared right here
next we have app dot static folder is
equal to static
this is just to specify the name of the
folder that contains static contents for
our application
coming back we have app.run host is
equal to localhost
this will run our application on the
local mission or the localhost
now let us move to the routes
so this is the home route or the default
route
what this code means is that when we
reach the home route index.html page
will be rendered let me show this to you
once
so this is the home page of our
application
this is nothing but
index.html web page as you can see here
i'll enter a forward slash and press
enter
this is bringing me back to the same
home page this just means that when we
reach the home route index.html page is
rendered
now let me try phrase level sentiment
analysis
this is the result page of phrase level
sentiment analysis
as you can see over here we have reached
forward slash predict route when we
reach forward slash predict route
results.html page will be rendered
now let me try out sentence level
sentiment analysis
this is the result page of sentence
level sentiment analysis as you can see
here we have reached forward slash
predict one route so we'll be using
predict one route to display the result
page of sentence level sentiment
analysis and will be using predict route
to display the result page of phrase
level sentiment analysis
now coming back to the code as i said
earlier we'll be using forward slash
predict round for phrase level sentiment
analysis
when we reach the predict route this
piece of code will get executed
it first checks if the request method is
post
if yes will we will fetch user input
values by using form controls and
transfer it to python variables for
example request.form of query this will
fetch values from input tag from
index.html page which has name attribute
as query since i am using a form action
so when the user clicks on the submit
button
whatever the value that he has entered
in this input tag will be associated
with the name query
and the same value will be transferred
to our python code and it will store in
this particular variable
and the same happens for request dot
form of num so the input tag which has
name attribute as num
this value will be transferred back to
the python code to this variable
next we are calling get tweets method
i'll explain get tweets method later on
basically what the get tweets method
does is that it takes query string and
count as an input and it will find all
the tweets that has query string in it
and it will predict each of the tweets
sentiment and return back the predicted
values to our variable right over here
the return value will be in the form of
list of dictionary elements
so i have given here an example of list
of dictionary elements as you can see
each of the dictionary elements has two
components one is the text and the other
one is sentiment so text is nothing but
the tweet itself
and the sentiment is nothing but the
predicted sentiment of that particular
tweet
finally we will render results.html page
along with that we'll be sending fetch
tweets result to it
as you can see here in results.html page
there is a variable called results
so the value for this variable will be
sending that from our python code so
whatever the value that is present in
the fetch tweets variable will be passed
on to the result variable in result.html
next we are doing a for each on result
and we are printing the tweet and its
corresponding sentiment in a tabular
format
next we have predict1 route
as i mentioned earlier predict1 route is
used for sentence level sentiment
analysis
here again similar to the predict route
we are taking a statement as an input
from the user and storing that in a
variable called text
next we are applying text blob method on
the input text
so to understand how the text block
works i'll show you that with an example
so this is the command prompt first i am
importing text blob
now let me take a variable answer is
equal to
text
text blob of
good morning
let us see what the answer variable has
answer variable has an object of text
blob
now i'll do an answer dot
sentiment
so this is returning a two values one is
the polarity and the other one is
subjectivity
the value that we need to concentrate is
the polarity value
now let me take another example
and now i'll do a text blob of
bad morning
now let us see what answer dot sentiment
returns it is returning a polarity value
of minus 0.699
let me take another example now we'll do
text blob of just morning
so
answer dot sentiment is returning a
polarity value of 0.0
what we can understand here is that when
the statement has a positive sentiment
then the polarity value is greater than
zero
similarly when the statement has a
negative sentiment the polarity value is
decreasing less than 0 in this case it
is reaching minus 0.698
and when the statement is neutral the
polarity remains at 0.
so we are using the same logic for our
project as well
we have implemented the same logic in
our code as well we are first finding
out what the polarity value is
and then we are checking if the polarity
value is greater than zero if it is
greater than zero then we are
classifying the sentiment as positive
if the polarity is equal to 0 then we
are classifying the sentiment as neutral
otherwise we will be classifying the
sentiment as negative
finally we will render
result1.html page
along with that we are passing the input
text message and the predicted sentiment
here in
result1.html we are using two different
variables msg and result and the values
for these two variables we are passing
it through our python code
now let us understand how get tweets
method works
takes three different arguments api
query and count so by default i have set
the account value as 5.
here i am converting the count value
into an integer value this is just to
make sure that we only have integer as a
value for count
next i am declaring a list over here
with the name of tweets and this is the
variable that we will be finally
returning from this method
as i had mentioned earlier the result of
get tweet method will be in the form of
a list of dictionary elements
and that is the reason why i have
declared a list over here as well
so for each of the tweet i will store
the text component and the sentiment
component in the form of a dictionary
and finally i will append these
dictionary values to the list
and that is how we will finally be
getting a list of dictionary elements so
i'll return the same variable
back to the calling method
this is the syntax to call for twitter
api
here we are specifying the api to do a
search we are also passing the query
string as an argument and we are
mentioning the language as english
and we are specifying the tweet mode as
extended
this tweet mode make sure that we get
the entire entire tweet not just a part
of it
finally we are limiting the total number
of tweets to the account specified by
the user
next we are doing a forage on each of
the tweets written by the twitter api
and for each of the tweets we are
extracting the full text value of the
tweet
and then to get the sentiment of the
tweets we are calling one more method
called get tweet sentiment
now let us see what get weight sentiment
looks like
so this is the
method definition of get tweet sentiment
as you can see it takes one argument
which is nothing but the tweet
i have actually mentioned here two ways
in which we can get the sentiment of
these tweets one is by using the nail
base analyzer and one is
without using any type of analyzer
you can use either but since this
code without specifying any analyzer is
much quicker than using the nail base
analyzer so i'll be sticking on to
this cone
but there is a slight change when you
use the nail base analyzer so instead of
getting the polarity of the tweet you
will get the classification itself and
the classification can either be
positive or negative you cannot get a
neutral classification in this method
as you can see here i am doing a text
blob method on the clean tweets clean
tweets is again a
separate method that
i have declared over here
clean tweet basically just removes
unwanted space
hashtags or any special characters from
the extracted tweets so it uses basic
regular expression to do that
so we are applying the text blob method
on the return clean tweets
again same as earlier we are extracting
the polarity value of the
of the answer and checking if the value
is greater than zero if it's greater
than zero then the sentiment is positive
if the polarity is equal to zero then
the sentiment is neutral
and finally if the polarity is less than
zero then the sentiment will be negative
so this is the logic behind get tweet
sentiment
if you like to use the naves analyzer
code all you need to do is that
comment these lines of code
and uncomment the name base analyzer one
just save this code and run it and you
will be able to get the same result
after getting the tweet and the
sentiment in the text and sentiment part
of our dictionary we will append the
same into our tweets list
the same process will happen for each of
the tweets finally by the end of this
loop we will get a list of dictionary
elements and that dictionary contains
all the tweets and its corresponding
sentiments
and this is the overall functioning of
app.py code
thanks a lot for watching i'll see you
guys in the next video